so we're going to go through majaya
number two now which is
sabasa translated as all the
defilements so the suta Begins by saying
the Buddha was staying near saati in
jeta Gro and he addressed the monks saying
Gro and he addressed the monks saying
monks I will teach you the EXP explation
of the Restraint of all
defilements uh listen and apply your
mind well I will
speak then the Buddha continues monks I
say that the ending of defilements is
for the one who knows and sees not for
the one who does not know or see for one
who knows and sees what attention
through source and attention through not
Source when you attend not through the
source defilements arise once Arisen
they grow when you attend through the
source defilements don't arise and those
that have already Arisen are given up
dispelled some defilements should be
given up by seeing some by restraint
some by using and some by bearing some
by avoiding and some by dispelling and
some by
developing so let's go to the beginning
of this where the Buddha says monks I
say that the ending of defilements is
for the one who knows and sees
not for the one who doesn't know or
see so this statement um means that the
teaching that's about to follow that the
the instructions he's about to give
apply to somebody who already has the
right view so at least the
S so the one who sees knows and sees the
way out of suffering not the one who
doesn't know and see way out of
suffering in other words if a person
without a Right View were to then just
try and do
uh andar things or develop things and
all these other things that the wdo will
describe one should do in the suta uh it
simply won't take place because they're
missing the prerequisite for it
prerequisite for it is as it says as it
continues here for one who um who knows
and sees what so what is it that
distinguishes a soap from AJ what is
what is that necessary prerequisite that
then makes rest of this the rest of the
Su apply that is attention through the
source and attention not through the
source or as as we probably people that
follow this channel they already know
the term p is yonis
manasara and ion
manasara uh we translated that in the
past as concurrent attention root
attention attention with the source um
basically yonara uh it's a it's a it's like 50% of
yonara uh it's a it's a it's like 50% of
the Right View let's put it that way um
in in the suta where the Buddha
describes that there are two
factors that for the rising of the Right
View uh one is utterance of another in
other words one is correct
instruction another one is yonar so you
could be talking to the Buddha himself
and he can be giving you the most
correct the most accurate
instruction you won't be understanding
it if Yara is not developed now
yonis manasar yonu means Womb manasara
means attention so womb attention uh the
source the origin attention like that
has been translated in in many different
ways and um so the point is like you you
know the common translation is like a
wise reflection or wise attention
implying it's something a person can
just do after some serious
consideration and you can take it to
mean that but then you should ask
yourself okay so if I have yonara
according to the meaning of wise
consideration for example so I am wisely
considering things and I got the right
instruction all the sutas all the all
the nikayas why am I not having the
Right View because these are the two
only factors for the Right View if
yonara meets the right instruction Right
View has to take place so then if a
person is honest they would ask
themselves well they would inquire
further and recognize that okay so it's
either not the right instruction or
perhaps my understanding of the first
factor of yonara it's not adequate and
that's the problem like these things
that we we would often say oh it's it's
it's wrong it's a wrong translation
itself it's not that they're completely
wrong so it's there's nothing wrong in
saying yasar is wise consideration
because yasara implies wise
consideration but
if if it's limited just to the uh
concept of wise consideration you won't
look further you won't make it even more
significant and
profound which is obviously necessary
because as as the sutta says as the
other sutta say yasara instruction of
another means the Right View there is no
third option
there so if there is no right view upon
meeting the teaching it's either because
the teaching is either wrong or you
don't have Yara you need to revise and
reconsider ironically what yonara means
and how deep that
goes so that's why the the insistence
and what I was translating in the past
calling it concurrent attention is just
it's just really more like just to to
kind of snap people out of that Slumber
of taking for granted oh yeah wise
reflection wise consideration I got that
I understand that while at the same time
knowing that they don't have the right
view so if you say it's a concurrent
attention or attention with the source
it's kind of it's confusing and that's
already a good starting point like you
won't be taking it for granted you will
take it as something that needs to be
clarified and
understood um so attention through the
source in in this translation that we
chose and attention not through the
source so
um you might wonder then what what
source is it like some sort of mystical
source and and what what source does
that refer to what is
it so think about it I mean we did a
whole like I don't know how many talks
on Yara and we can probably link them
here in the
description um so people should like if
they won't understand it or or get a um
bigger wider picture on on on the
indication of what it actually means uh
they should definitely listen to those
talks so like in brief here now without
going into dedic this whole talk just to
discussion of Yono attention with the
source or through the source even better
again implies the simultaneous presence
of say that which you're attending
whatever that might be particular
General internal external personal not
personal doesn't matter whatever your
current mind currently your mind is
occupied with attending at attending U
two simultaneous to that there is a
simultaneous presence of a necessary
basis for
that so whatever you were doing whatever
action you were engaged with like your
attention naturally goes with that
direction and and Falls onto what you
are doing so the the content of what
you're doing so that's why like the the
sensuality is one of the chief examples
of AAR of attending not through the
source or not with the source
simultaneously recognized there uh you
you get
overly um concerned overly invested
overly concentrated onto the objects of
your senses as opposed to not losing the
sight not losing the context the
perspective of whatever you are
attending through your senses the
necessary basis the source of that whole
attending uh to this particular thing
that arose on account of my sight the
necessary basis is simultaneously
present there as a necessary basis
if that basis is removed if that source
is taken away no experience standing
upon it can remain and that is a
recognition that bujina can develop can
develop if he goes in that direction of
of Yono which obviously he has to if he
wants to get the right view so in the in
in a more like a in Practical examples
the source is like uh well you could say
like for example if it's um if it's the
the central object you're looking at the
necessary Source the that's
simultaneously pres present there it's
uh you could you could describe it as
it's the uh necessity of the body more
specifically necessity of the eye organs
which is the basis the field for which
on which these things can be discerned
now people forget that people don't
think about their eyes when they're
preoccupied with a lustful sight or even
disagreeable sight they they they they
look past the experience right here so
in like when you're experiencing sight
sound smell taste touches you
experiencing your senses experiencing
sight sound smell taste touches but
those senses as an underlying basis are
overlooked people see saon smelt touches
directly or they assume it's a direct
connection direct perception of sight
sounds smell taste touches over there in
the world yet really the closest to the
direct connection is just you being
aware of what your senses are perceiving
without seeing the senses overlooking
the source so when you attend to the
sense objects you don't attend through
the necessary basis of those sense
objects you completely ignore it you're
unaware of it that's the point so it's
Discerning that which is seemingly
invisible your eye is invisible in your
sights yet is a necessary basis for
sights to exist so not losing the
context of the necessity of the eyes
when you are looking at the SES is
already close to Yono
Yara so you might still be attending to
the sense objects but not at the expense
of ignoring the necessary basis for
those sense objects you can go even
further uh you can discern the Yono
manasara of your current uh currently
currently performed action so say you
are engaging in some action say you're
writing something you're writing a
letter as an example intention to write
a letter that binds all these acts of
getting the paper
taking the pen opening the paper writing
down the sentences ideas what you want
to say that whole thing it's all
contained within still having the
intention to finish to write and
complete this letter because if halfway
through that letter intention to not
write a letter the State of Mind changes
you'll stop writing the letter and
that's another thing that the people
would Overlook ignore or be unaware of
when they act they don't see their
intentions that they behind those
actions giving them meaning to all the
subsequent particular things you do to
complete that action they remain unified
with your original intention that
intention doesn't go away it's not
sitting there in the past it's carried
through by all these actions that you
engaging with so these are the examples
of discerning through the source now
that in and of itself will not give rise
to the to the right view if you're just
Discerning through the source obviously
would give rise to some degree of wisdom
and some degree of withdrawal from being
overly absorbed in sense objects but it
won't give rise to the right view in
even in and of itself but if somebody
does have that way of attending not
overlooking a a a degree that's hiding
there in the middle like your eyes are
hiding between oh me here and looking at
things over there that you just
assume uh and so if you if you have
developed that recognition and you get
the right instruction that points at
that middle way the the the utterance of
another the right view is inevitable
it cannot not occur that's the point so
and that's exactly why the Buddha
describes it here he like the ending of
the defilement so basically the The
Liberation from suffering is for the one
who knows and sees not for the one who
doesn't know and see knowing see what
that middle ground that which is usually
invisible in people's actions in
people's perception of of of sight sound
smell taste touches stuff that they
Overlook stuff that they needs to they
need to be pointed at in order to start
to discern it the necessary basis of
certain things even again you will never
be able to see your eyes yet you can
hammer in like on the individual basis
of every perception and in general that
it's impossible it will be impossible to
see if eye organs stop working is just
inconceivable so simply that which
starts as an abstract thought of oh my
eye organs are because of which I'm
seeing this start including into every
time you engage with sights sound smell
taste touches respective organs you
would not be able to be to experience
the any kind of sense of touch uh
presence of the body here and now if
there is not that living physical body
over there simultaneously existing or
over here you can say it so the point is
not to to to to try to attend to what
that Source might be because that would
be on the level of already attending to
the objects of your senses including
mentally uh uh the point is to discern
the necessity of the source while your
attention is resting on this or that so
that's how that's why sense restraint is
necessary to just force you to withdraw
from the dependence on the sense objects
and the degree that your mind kind of is
engaged with and once you withdrawn from
that overly proliferated dependence on
the sense objects you actually then get
to well you could there is at least some
possibility that then you get to discern
ah necessity of the phenomenon of the
living eyes that exist simultaneous to
the things I'm seeing and I'm engaged
with so just to that degree you don't
need to then seek and find out what
those eyes really are you want what
those eyes really are is that uh an
invisible aspect that's simultaneously
present in the opposite direction of
whatever you are currently
attending in the nutshell that's your
only and you could see okay you could
still take it to mean wise reflection
but what what if you take it to me
something to mean something as deep as I
just described something as hard to see
as I just
described is it really farfetched then
then taking it to mean uh uh in such
manner plus instruction of another oh
yeah then the right view is certainly
more possible it certainly makes even
more sense like if you are already
Discerning all all the undermining
everything you see here smell taste
touch think for that matter every
everything you do you're undermining by
recognition of the necessary basis for
it that cannot be yours at the same time
that's not yours that has its own field
that has its own existence that has its
own course that has its own
characteristics then you recognize oh
okay if I start seeing my whole
experience undermine in that manner and
I get the right instruction of where the
Dua is it's it's it's very likely I will
be able to understand it but
if I remain just regarding reading the
Su and thinking yisu is just that wise
reflection just sit down and consider
things before you do them which is nice
nobody denies that but it's not deep
enough it does not undermine your sense
of presence Here and Now enough for the
Dharma to apply so that's that's kind of
the point and often we'll come across
that especially if we go through this
these um sutta studies it's not like
that common translations are wrong just
they're not accurate
enough like and you could see like say
if you if you are rightly considering
the necessary basis the necessity of the
organs living functioning organs of your
eyes simultaneously present while you're
looking at this thing now any lust any
aversion whatever might be that level of
Engagement will be bracketed will be put
second to the necessary basis for it
that's why it's like eye organ sites or
anything in between as the sutas often
describe he experienced this passion
toward words because it's undermined
rightly so when and whenever there is
absence Whenever there is last aversion
delusion undermind there is a rising of
wisdom so you could see that if you take
Yono to mean this what we just what I'm
describing here and now and now it's
like oh yeah that includes wise
reflection for sure like you cannot
unwisely reflect unwisely while you're
simultaneously undermining Your Lust
aversion loss of perspective with the
right order so if there is no lust if if
or there's diminishing of lust
diminishing of version diminishing of
delusion there is pretty
much um non there's an increase in the
right perspective so if you're not lustful
perspective so if you're not lustful
you're less likely well if you're not
lustful you will not be unreasonable
whenever people are unreason
unreasonable whenever they lose context
lose perspective it's on account of last
version of delusion there's no other
option there um so if you take yis to
mean this and then work towards
understanding it then you will need very
little instruction to apply because this
is already 50% of the work and that's
exactly why it's so important and the
whole Sut starts with
that ending of suffering ending of
defilement is for the one who sees not
for the one who doesn't see doesn't see
what Yar and AAR he sees the degree he
sees the extent he sees that
simultaneous relationship and then continues so when
relationship and then continues so when
you attend not through the source
defilements G verion delusion
increase and once Arison they
grow when you attend through the source
defilements don't arise and once Arisen
they diminish and that that's actually
in another Su where the Buddha talks
about hindrances where people commonly
think hindrances you deal with
hindrances by countering them by doing
this when this hindrance is present when
doing that when this hindrance is
present but actually the whole suit
sums up the whole five hces you deal
with them by seeing through them with
Yara so that's the point see yasar is a
factor that puj can develop with the
right instruction from another he can
become a s and that that Yar doesn't
it's not finished the entire like
development of that practice that
follows for from aana to arant is just
done through expanding the yonara until
there is no part of your
experience no part of your Aggregates
that you could possibly attend wrongly
with iono so that habit of seeing with
Yono is is is is Thoroughly has
thoroughly permeated all the aspects of
your experience even like the five
hindrances abandoning them you abandon
them by seeing through them so by seeing
their Source the necessary present basis
of an arisen sensuality you see it as a
necessary present basis of a is subba
image uh picture of beautiful image of
beautiful notion of beautiful that you
haven't undermined you undermine it
there and then that which was the
hindrance remains you become unhindered
by and he goes on for all the other
we'll come to that suta at some point
and obviously I'll I'll I'll I'll
reference it here but the point is that
uh and in other suta Yes actually the
Buddha said there is not a single thing
that makes sensuality uh makes the Aris
sensuality increase non Aris sensuality
arise such as
ionis and there is not a single thing in
the world that makes the Arisen
sensuality diminish and non Arisen
sensuality not arise uh as yonar so
learning how to undermine things rightly
through attending with the source in
other words whatever you're attending
you're Discerning the source present
there simultaneously with it is the way
they would free
not just from sensuality but from the
hindrances and from all the defilements
and this Su just confirms that because
when the Buddha describes these types of
defilements and then we go now to the
first defilement which is defilement to
be given up by
seeing so he says what are the
defilements that should be given up by
seeing take an untrained ordinary person
putuj who is neither skilled or trained
in the teaching of the noble ones hasn't
seen them has not discerned it they've
not seen the true person in other words
they don't have the right instruction
they don't have
y they don't they don't understand they
don't see for themselves internally
intimately they don't see which things
they should attend like which things
they should allow their attention to
rest on and which things they should not
allow their attention to rest on so in
order to see which things you should
allow your attention to rest on and
which things that aren't suitable for
attention you need to become a s first
so Pua cannot discern that so there are
10 things they shouldn't and they don't
attend things they should they don't
know where the emphasis is as I often
say so they and then explains what are
those things that they attended they
shouldn't well they are things that when
attended to give rise to unisen
defilements and make the Arison
defilements grow defilements of central
desire defilements of being Bava and
ignorance so they things that they
attend but they shouldn't so it's
they're attending them and the way
they're attending them that's another
mistake and then there things that if you stop
and then there things that if you stop
attending in that wrong way they will
not give rise to to Unison uh UNH
wholesome and uh things in
defilements so if you don't attend
sensual desire if you don't attend being
wrongly if you don't attend
ignorance those things will not
increase um but in order to know that in
order to discern those things you
already need to have the right View and
you already need to have Yara
obviously so
so
having uh not knowing putuj not knowing
what should he attend he attends to
things he attends to unsuitable things
he attends to suitable things wrongly he
basically he doesn't know where the
measure is so when they're not attending
through the
source um iono
manasar then the questions such as did I
exist in the past did I not exist in the
past was I in the past how was I in the
past after being what what did I become
um the questions about the future will I
exist in the future will I not exist in
the future what will be the Future How
will I be in the future after being what
what will I become or they are undecided
about the present am I am I not what am
I how am I is everything Ana oh this is
Ana there is really anata this is anata
everything is an not that the Buddha
said but fundamentally they don't see
that for themselves so it's all just on
the level of uh concerned guas work so
to speak and that's all result of
cultivating ionara of of not seeing things through
ionara of of not seeing things through
the source that they have
Arisen and by doing so by by doing so
yes by doing the the
iara you of course in inevitably
inadvertently put yourself as the center
of the experience that's what's
emphasized me seeing me hearing and so
on um and that's that's pretty much that
root of ownership and through all the
problems so then through continuing such
ways of thinking and uh emphasizing
things wrongly the natural questions the
natural concerns of the PJ would be
where did I come from where will I go
all these insecurities that revolve
around me and my placement and my
security and even if they don't think
about the past or don't think about the
future presently they will be unclear
and undecided in other words they will
still hold onto that view of the themsel
as the center of the experience CU they
haven't undermined the center of the
experience sufficiently
enough so that's what I said if you stop
attending wrongly to to lust to to
aversion to being to delusion to
ownership to all these things this will
diminish even if you're still penous
even if you still hold a self viw to
some degree if you haven't heard the
Buddhist teaching if you don't know
don't know the way out of the dukka by
not attending wrongly to all these
things that should not be attended to
wrongly these views will diminish and
you will not have the pressuring
question of where am I heading what will I be
of where am I heading what will I be
what's my future you know will I be
liberated all these these anxious kind
of things that concern oneself
deeply um so and then he says so if they
continue when they don't so when they're
where they're attending to things
wrongly do not discern Yono and keep
attending to things with Aon manasar
without without the source so to speak
without the recognition of the source
and then they continue engaging with
such questions was I in the past who was
how did this come to be and oh what's
samsara and how did we originate where
we are heading all that kind of these
answers that people seek to basically
provide a sense of um Clarity and
security for their concern about their
future selves where will I end up what
will happen to me will it go up or down
you know all these anxious things that
will kind of Arise at some point so if a
person continues doing that and tries
seeking answer on that level already on
the basis of all the wrong assumption in
I so the Buddha says when they attend
not through the source in this way one
of the following six views arises for
them there is myself there's not myself
I perceive self the self with the self I
perceive the not self with the self I
perceive the self with what is not self
what view canot arise in them is I
perceive not self with not self because
for that they need to have had undermine
their experience sufficiently enough
through Yar so that's why often you have people
Yar so that's why often you have people
talk about oh yes you know the the
modern science has proven the Buddha as
well that everything is impermanent us
nothing is real no that's very much the
wrong view like it's not a question that
view like it's not a question that
things are not real the question is that
things are not your yours even if you
want them to be so the sense of self the
center of experience that you are you
can deny you can say well this sense of
self is just composed out of atoms and
chemicals in this body and thus it's not
mine but you still see that not self
that you described through your sense of
self because there is
ionis or other way around through not
through the sense of not self you see
self either permutation whichever way
you reflect back there's going to be a
sense of self High hiding there or
implicit there cuz you can't just
willingly step outside of it you can
only undermine it through Yono and the
right instruction so it's not incidental
that these six views there is self or
there is no self which you say which
which you perceive which is sent of self
I perceive the self with self there is
self on every level no no no some things
are not self some things are self this
is not my self uh yesterday was myself
today is not myself either way past
future present uh in personal in
personal there's going to be self hiding
at some level in other words a wrong
emphasis would be hiding at some
level but it's not incidental that
within this U six views so these are the
five and then the sixth view is the self
of mine is he the speaker The knower Who
experiences the result of good bad and
again this is like obviously a template
phrase but you could read the subtlety
into and recognize it you know when
people say oh yeah nothing's real
everything is AATA there is just the
knowing of the experience there just the
Noah the the pure Consciousness the
Eternal chit all these things that
people say all those things are
personified to that extent all of those
things is now what their self has become
and where it is hiding doesn't matter
how you Rebrand it or how you call it if
you are giving an entity a phenomenon
Superior position from which The Knowing
happens and perception and Liberation
and eternal Freedom that entity is going
to be your sense of self cuz that's what
you start with so the question is not
finding the super special thing that can
be your sense of self that's that's
anata and that's free from everything
the question is undermining everything
until you can't hold on to things even
if you want to so that's why nobody can
do the practice of the Right View
accidentally because it goes against the
entire being that you are against the
grain of it against everything that that
your inclination would go you have to
swim against them swim against the
stream as the Buddha described but the
point is is uh you can't do that
accidentally you have to have had some
sort of faith in some sort of
instruction that is now making you
constantly undermine your experience
through seeing the necessary present
Source here and now and by doing so to
that extent make yourself unable to own
or or assume the ownership or
appropriate things that you're
perceiving like your senses see by being
by overlooking your eyes and being
engaged with the sight delighting in it
relishing it you have a appropriated
your eyes simply by not seeing that as a
necessary basis over there independent
of of your seeing so to speak
independent in a sense of it's not in
your control so it's not in incidental that
control so it's not in incidental that
these views do not allow for somebody to
perceive not self with not self top to
bottom to be free from the atada from
the self view because for that they need
to have had stopped attending to these
things with iono and in order to do that
they need to have had been sufficiently
restrained withdrawn so they're not
giving the the attention to things they
shouldn't be
giving and
uh and then the Buddha concludes this by
saying this is called going into views a
Thicket of views u a desert of views a
contortion of views a Fed of views a
writhing of
views and then being feted by these
views an untrained ordinary person is
not freed for birth old age death sorrow
limitation pain sadness and distress
they are not free from suffering I say
now take the train Noble disciple the
one with the Right View they understand
for themselves which things they should
attend and which things they should not
attend um and they understand that
things that they shouldn't attend is the
one that make the defilements arise and
on a reason manifest and the reason one
grow such as sensuality being in
ignorant so it repeats this and then
they understand that the things that
they if they are attended to they don't
give rise to these UNH wholesome States
so then they stick to it they don't
attend to things they shouldn't and
attend to the the things they should so
then the unisen defilements don't arise
and those defilements that are Arisen
they're given
up they attend through the source in
other words they
recognize um the nature of their
situation here and now see when you
attend through the
source of the necessity of the eye
organs for your sites or just take
overall necessity of this physical lamp
of Flesh which is the body for your
experience as a whole it's a necessary
basis while you're attending particular
aspect of the aspects of the experience
as a whole well when you're attending to
that with the right instruction you get
to recognize the certain characteristic
of that necessary basis of that
condition of those eye organs or the
body as a whole which is it's
impermanent it's not pleasurable being
paired with a moving vehicle that you
have no control over its directions it's
actually when you recognize oh this is
uneasy this this cannot be any pleasure
experience is contingent to the fact
that this vehicle is still moving in the
direction that can lead to my tremendous
pedal so simple recognition of Unown
ability of the body on that yonis level
not like oh this is not mine this is not
mind this is unable no no seeing it as a
necessary basis for attending to it even
if it's the same body you're attending
that necessary basis is
unable that source is unable that Source
thus because it's unable came on its own
it's subject to its own directions
inconceivable doesn't see you you don't
exist for it thus it cannot be in your
possession eternally it cannot remain
unchanged internally and that all
becomes implicit so that's why when I
saw who has stopped attending to wrong
things who has developed
yonara who has received instruction of
what to look for in terms of suffering
he recognizes when he attends through
the source he recognizes this is the
suffering this is the origin of
suffering this will be the ending of
that suffering and this is the practice
that would cement that cessation of that
suffering they would cement that freedom
because that's exactly what the
suffering is it's not in this or this
sight sound smell taste touches past
future no no no it's the in the
Perpetual relationship between the
necessary basis and your life and things
you engag with with the necessary basis
of that source and things you're
attending through that well with or
without that recognition of that Source
that's what the suffering is once he
recognizes that all the concerns about
past future who he was what he will be
where he's heading it's all diminished
so when somebody recognizes the
relationship between the source and
things they're attending at the same
time there is the source of their
experience of attending to this thing or
that thing they have recognized the
dharm and by by doing so they give up
the three FS as the Su describes they
give the ownership view Sak or
personality view depending on what
translation you look at uh they give
doubt and they give uh grasping of the
virtues and virtue and practices or
holding on to still about AP paramas we
have other talks on that as well maybe
we'll link that too um basically they
give uh wrong view of there is a self
that's the center of the experience
independent of these Aggregates
independent of s smell test touches that
perceive smell stast see and so on here
um they give up doubt in regard to what
the origin is what the actual source is
they can still doubt mundane stuff but
they can't doubt the presence of the
source while they're doubting so that's
why becomes inaccessible to doubt see
when you're in the experience of
doubting you're attending to your doubt
there is the present Source enduring as
a necessary basis for you to be engaged
in the experience of doubt it is real as
such and they have thoroughly discerned
that and that's inaccessible to doubt as
the sutas would describe
that and um so they give up doubt and
then they give up the dependence the
sense the view of Duty that the practice
is on the level of external mechanical
things that come through your sense
objects or by doing this by doing that
by holding on to this by believing that
so techniques meth methods U external
authorities um all that is given up
because that's never where the practice
was and that's never where the suffering
was so then number two
um now number two are the defilements to
be given up by
restraint and the word for restraint is
SAR kept in cheack basically restrained
so take a monk who reflecting through
the source so Panka
Yono he lives restraining The Faculty of
the eye so in other words reflecting
through the source it's like broadening
of your yonara it's like increasing the
basis so it's a practice so you have
yonis so you see the necessary source
and now you are you increasing that
basis of that source so that you don't
actively have to keep reminding yourself
but it stays there as a
context so being established in such habit of
so being established in such habit of
reflecting through yonara or with yonara
he lives restraining The Faculty of the
eye so he restrains his eyes from seeing
things that would give rise to last and
so on even before he sees them because
he recognizes that
uh distressing and feverish defilement
that might arise in someone who lives
without the restraint will not arise in
me if I live with the restraint so he's
already undermined UNH wholesome he
recognize un wholesome he's undermining
on the level of the view but now he
needs to practically practice engage
with preventing his eyes from going back
to this the remnants of these old habits
of seeking pleasure in sights and
forgetting about the necessary basis of
the living body The Source that's unable
that's that's danger that's Peril that's
like a chopping block not forgetting
that is then maintained simply through
not allowing your eyes to distract
themselves that's in the natural the the
purpose of the restraint you start doing
it externally so that then BEC this
internal criteria of Yar is developed
and then you maintain that simply
through not allowing your eyes to look
at things that they shouldn't so it
becomes like a effortless maintenance
and development of Yar which means it
becomes like develop uh effortless
development of the path simply through
not doing certain things not letting
your eyes look at UNH wholesome sites
and same goes like uh reflected through
the source restraining the restraining
the fact facy of ear nose tongue body
and the
mind and these are the defilements that
should be given up by restraint so
obviously somebody without sayuj without
Yara if he practices restraint he will
he will also not give rise to these
states that would beset the mind with
defilement and so on but uh in and of
itself that restraint will not bring
Yono manasara to to increase and become
fortified because they haven't develop
that so you should still practice
sensory straint even if you were not a
soop because that can help you develop
Yara but this practice here it's done
through Yara which is why in return it
feeds it that's what I mean like by
simply not engaging with UNH hold from s
sound smell taste touches once Yono is
developed so a certain a whole a whole
layer for a la of better word of
defilements are simply given up through
restraint that's it for the one with the
Right View view not for the one without
the Right View I'll keep repeating
that number three defilements given up
by
using so what are those defilements well
take a monk who reflecting through the
source makes use of robes only for the
sake of wording off cold heat Touch of
flies mosquitoes wind Sun reptiles for
covering up the private parts reflecting
through the source he makes the use of
arms food not for fun not for adornment
not for decoration but only to sustain
the body AO avoid the harm support the
the spiritual practice avoid illness and
stuff like
that so in this way I should put an end
to all this Comfort not give rise to new
discomfort and I will live blamelessly
and it is reflecting through the source
he makes the use of lodgings for the
sake of Waring of cold heat Touch of
Lies mosquitoes windson reptiles from
harsh weather and to enjoy Retreat
seclusion reflecting through the source
he makes use the medicines and supplies
for the sick only for the sake of Waring
of the Pains of illness and promote good
health for the distressing and feverish
defilements might arise in someone who
lives without using these things they do
not arise when they used rightly so in
this case again it's certain Necessities
such as shelter food uh
clothes um medicines even those things
are not taken for granted like oh I must
do this because illness is bad yes
illness is bad illness will prevent you
but any any engagement with doing with
taking medicine or or having a shelter
or looking looking for a shelter or
looking for robes is always maintained
kept in check through through
maintaining through
reflecting um through the source in this
case Source being the wholesome context
the necessary context that's practically
relevant for your practice so uh he
seeks the lodgings with this uh seeking
of the lodging is um is informed is is
is decided upon if the criteria are met
that are suitable for practice not the
criteria that come out of one's
preference uh or one's habits so it's
like what do I need for practice well I
need shelter from from the elements from
the cold I need U not overly exposed and
need seclusion and then you seek a place
that meets that and that's it you don't
go further because the need has been met
and and again that's what I I saying in
the beginning like one of the ways of
discerning yasara is through your
engagement with things and why you're
doing them so if you are eating why are
you eating if you don't ask that
question yourself you'll be eating for
the wrong reasons because that's how we
all start so you need to actively keep
re uh re uh retraining your own
intention in other words yes you can
ignore that ignore the the necessity of
food for practice and eat just because
of pleasure or because of boredom or
because of whatever else or you can make
the effort hold on no no no I will
recollect and frequently Ponder and
maintain the context that food is only
so that I can practice uh ending of
suffering that's it that's my I will
allow myself only to that extent to
engage with the with the food so then
see when you're choosing what to eat
without losing that context that Yono
that source of Your Action of
eating it will be uh much less likely
that you will be choosing solely based
on the preference you'll be choosing
more like what will last the longest
what will keep me the fullest for the
smallest amount what will not make me
feel heavy and sluggish and sleepy but
what will provide the necessary
nutrients um so that and you have to
maintain that every time you eat you
mustn't lose perspective so if every
time you eat every time you wear clothes
every time you engage with a shelter or
seek shelter or live in a shelter you
don't lose the context why this
environment is as such and what is its
purpose and if if a monk with the Right
View practices that a whole layer of
defilements will be abandoned simply on
account of that then defilements to be
given uh by bearing so by putting up so
take monks who reflected through the
source Bears cold heat hunger thirst
Bears the touch of flies mosquitoes wind
reptiles he Bears rude and unwelcome
criticism he puts up with physical pain
sharp severe acute unpleasant
disagreeable life-threatening so in
other words
a degree of discomfort has to be
experienced sooner or later it will come
and see if there are no flies and
mosquitoes and you live in comfortable
environment well there is the rude words
and unwelcome criticism people talking
badly about you see it's on the level of
you have to put up with it through the
yonis through the just so when the
experience of the bad words is present
you don't try to counter it defend
yourself show that they're wrong and so
on no no no you need to develop your
yisu in regard to it that's how you deal
with it so you bear it so that you can
see the source of it and but if you just
do that to that extent even if you don't
have to seek out the actual physical
discomfort sooner or later they they
will come
obviously uh simply thinking what
somebody said about you that you didn't
like somebody might say somebody is
saying you already recognize oh see
there is the gratuitous resistance to
that discomfort of words of another or
too much cold too too cold too hot
insects biting it's all on the same
level so how do I deal with it by
bearing so by not acting out of it by
seeing through it Discerning the source
of it so when those things are present
you're not attending to who said what
you're allowing that to be while you're
attending to the source of it correctly
yasara and if you do that the whole set
of defilements the whole layer of them
will be given up simply by bearing them
with the Right View not without it
defilement is given up by
avoiding so what are the defilements one
should one should give up by avoiding
well take a monk who reflect through the
source avoids a wild elephant a wild
horse a wild ox wild dog a snake a stump
thy ground a pit Cliff swamp or a
sewer reflecting through the source he
avoids sitting on inappropriate seats
walking inappropriate neighborhoods
mixing with bad friends so this is again
somebody who has the right View recogn
izes that they still have work to do
they're still not an Arun so it's wise
for them even if it's out of fear or or
distress to to avoid a murderer avoid
where wild elephants might kill you yes
there is a degree oh I'm afraid I'm
affected by this I shouldn't be affected
by this that's correct but the way to
not be affected by it is to become an
Arun in order to become an Arun you'll
need time because it needs to be
developed and in order to have time you
need to not be killed there and then so
avoiding things that will end your life
here and now while at the same time
because at the same time you recognize
that you have not completed the work so
let me complete the work free from this
imminent danger and then when imminent
danger comes and you're an Arun well you
might decide not to move if there is a
wild elephant doesn't matter uh the the
followup the next paragraph that that
continues reflecting through the souls
he avoids sitting in inappropriate seats
inappropriate neighborhoods mixing with
bad friends this refers to and again
even putuj can practice this to degree
this refers to like not putting yourself
in the situation or situations that can
then compromise your sense restraint and
your prets so in this particular this
refers to among so avoiding
inappropriate seats would be secluded
seeds with a female present that then
can give rise to either things being
said out of lust or done out of lust
they wouldn't have even been possible no
matter even if he wasn't an Arun and
free from sensuality if he didn't even
sit in that uh inappropriate secluded
hidden seat private seat that um if he
didn't even sit there no subsequent
things would have taken place so
somebody recognizes that I won't even
put myself in that position and then I
have nothing to deal with it um in other
words I will not have broken the rules
compromised the sense restraint and
everything else they could possibly
follow for somebody who's not completely
free so through rightfully reflecting
that there is still work to be done he
avoids it it's not like yeah but you
know I'm Beyond this I should be able to
sit that and so when you complete the
work you might but then you won't be
doing it for those reasons and certainly
those possibilities of breaking the
precepts losing the sense restraint
would not be there as options same
walking inappropriate neighborhoods
mixing with bad friends in other words
bad friends they can put you
inadvertently in bad situations so it's
like foreseeing those things from the
context of yonara and the work that
still needs to be done and then avoiding
those things once you foree see
them and by doing that you abandon all
the defilements that come that would
come with
it so what are the defilements the monk
should give up by dispelling so take a
monk who um reflecting through the
source he does not tolerate Central
aversive or cruel thought that has
arisen he gives it up gets rid of it
eliminates it obliterates it and that's
that other Su that di mention he
actually explains how one gets rid of it
um because people usually
like people come to read the
sutas with preconceived notions already
with some ideas what practice is so
generally today you are thought whenever
these things are present get rid of it
you know uh Central thought replace it
with this thought this replace with that
thought so you don't have to deal with
it you actually you don't have to endure
the weight of it you don't have to
discern it and um and then when people
read the suta it kind of or suas like
this I was like oh yes see the Buddha
says you get rid of it you obliterate it
it's like yes the Buddha says say that
but he also says how you do it and he
certainly doesn't say oh you get rid of
it simply by doing the opposite or by
focusing on your nostrils and so on he
says reflecting through the source you
you dispel it uh we link that suta where
where it clearly describes that for the
five Aggregates so the for sorry for the
five hindrances not Aggregates so when
there's a hindrance of sensuality
present like if all your concern is to
get rid of it get rid of it Focus away
concentr on something else distract
yourself from it if you distract
yourself from the
hindrance you will not be able to see
what is the necessary basis for the
hindrance how can you discern through
the source through to the source if your
preoccupation is hindrance get rid of it
hindrance Look Away Focus away calm down
get the nostrils belly whatever you
focus on just so I don't have to have
this pressure in me that's why again all
this dispelling all this doesn't doesn't
tolerate uh he gives you up gets rid of
eliminates apply only to somebody who
soana so first you need to get the right
view you need to develop Yara get the
right view then you'll be able to to see
through the central thought a ver and by
seeing through you are not tolerating it
by seeing through the nature of the say
site that you are preoccupied with full
of lust seeing through the necessary
basis to that extent see you're not now
perpetuating gratuitously that sense
objects of pleasure and so on same with
aversion same with the thought of
cruelty and same like again so sound Mel
States thoughts it's the same principle
so he doesn't tolerate this harmful
States in other words he does not
neglect his work of Discerning the
necessary Source that's simultaneously
present that's how you don't tolerate it
um and then it says the one who
practices this no defilements can arise
and this is the called defilements that
should be given up B dispelling so as I
said we will link the suta where where
would describes five
hindrances and I'm repeating this
because it's very relevant so it's not
about when you have a hindrance of ill
will hindrance of sleeping it's not like
I'll do the opposite I'll do the
mechanical thing of focusing away of
something else or visualizing thing no
no no you recognize what pressures you
so that you can discern the necessary
basis for that pressure and that's how
you become unpressured and that sign of
beauty that for somebody with ionara
means Central hindrance remain standing
there because that's what Buddha said
for tagata there is no desire and last
internally uh beautiful things remain
standing in the world it's not that he
doesn't perceive what used to be ins
incentive of lust and so on but in order
to get there you need to first get that
pressure recognize the pressure of the
hindrance not try to just immediately
blindly distract yourself get rid of it
but discern the necessary basis and
that's how you dispel it I gave the
simul many times in the past from the
sutas where it's like like a turtle that
the Jack Jackal tries to bite its Limbs
and the turtle how does the turtle deal
with the Mara and temptations and ways
of trying to get the turtle to stick its
limbs out by retracting inside
sufficiently long enough then the Jackal
lose interest and then you can walk away
and this is it basically by perceiving
through the pressuring hindrance that
pressure will be taken away from you and
then once you cultivate that yonu
sufficiently repeatedly uh thoroughly
then then even that pressure won't arise
anymore so you would have truly
dispelled the hindrances arant is the
destroyer of the hindrances they cannot
arise for him that's what that
means so
uh so we are now to defilements to be
given up by
developing and that's uh again here
through yonara through through correct
context of
yonara uh develops The Awakening
liberating factor of mindfulness
recollection Sati he develops the factor of
Sati he develops the factor of
discrimination of phenomena discernment
which is
dich he develops the enlightenment
factor of effort Vara energy Zeal uh to
do the work he develops the uh
Enlightenment factor of pity which is um
Joy satisfaction PADI tranquil tranquility
satisfaction PADI tranquil tranquility
and composure which is samadi
so again these things are developed
through yonara by somebody who has the right
yonara by somebody who has the right
View and the final is the equinity which
rely on withdrawal dispassion sensation
and ripen in
relinquishment and through developing
these factors he would have abandon all
defilements through that development so
if a monk through
yonara gives up the defilements by
seeing by restraint by using by enduring
or bearing by avoiding by
dispelling by developing he's the monk
that has surmounted and restrained and
withdrawn from all the defilements he
has cut off the craving unti untied the
fets sever the fetas and he rightly
comprehend uh and right by rightly
comprehending the slightest traces of
his conceit basically are gone so there
is no more even traces of I am and that
flavor of of of of ownership and things
being Mar
and thus he has made a complete end to
suffering so um satisfied the monks
approved what the Buddha
said U so that yeah that kind
of concludes the s number two and uh I
don't want to go through like just a
brief recap basically it's like a for
somebody who is not
Sana obviously like the Su doesn't apply
to you but as I said in the previous
recording it's not like you you should
not try and align yourself with it but
the reason why I keep saying it doesn't
apply to you because it's very easy for
somebody with the Right View read the
sutas that are not addressed to them for
them they don't meet the necessary
criteria for it but you could still make
sense out of them see you read the Su
like oh yeah okay I can do enduring I
can do bearing I can do this I can do
that I can eat for Right Reasons uh and
then ignore or rather stop thinking that
they also need to develop the yonara
that is the necessary basis for all of
this to be done rightly so because you
make some sense out of it you'll stop
looking for further sense in it and
that's really the the only reason why I
keep insisting well nope the dhama
starts with the Right View if you're not
a sodana you do not see the dharm if
you're not sodana most of the S don't
apply to you because if you don't see
what the practice is how can you
practice different aspects of that
practice it's just makes no sense it's
not just to to to put people down or
something it's more like just to to
prevent from falling into thinking that
you know that which you don't and you
can easily fall into that once you start
making sense of all these other things
oh yeah you know Sati patana and all of
this and anapanasati of course it's
relatable to a degree you can see some
sense in it but it's not on the level
that it matters even this as we started
the Su y wise reflection consider it
reflection whatever people
translated you could see exactly where
that translation came from came from
making a sense out of it but if you're
actually honest and see but hold on in
other suit it said that that is a factor
for soap so did my wise consideration
and instruction of others is that
resulting in s party when I engage with
it when I engage with it or do I have to
keep doing it do I have to keep wisely
reflecting each time I'm presented with
these challenges and so on cuz then you
realize okay so maybe maybe it's not it
doesn't match the extent that the Buddha
meant by it uh and uh and you have
nothing to lose if you take it to mean
more you can only gain see if it only
meant wise reflection you were already
right by thinking that from the start
but if it means even something that that
contains wise reflection but means even
more such as Discerning the necessary
basis of the present enduring source of
that which you're
attending if you discern that well it's
a win-win either way
so that's why for as long as there is no
right view one should really um take any
suta that they read with a pinch of salt
and not forget the fact that if you were
to fully understand any relevant suta
you know not the suta that talks about
like Buddha instructing householders how
to look after their wives and stuff like
that that's irrelevant certain
Irrelevant for the one who wants to
practice so if you take any sutta that's
practically relevant you you mustn't
forget that if I were to understand this
suta on the level that matters I'll be at
on the level that matters I'll be at
least a
s and if I were to fully understand it I
would be an Arun like people often did
at the end of the
suta and the point is then to to keep
that in mind each time like wisely
reflect um that each time you read the
suta that should be the the the the
threshold that you need to need to hold
in your mind for understanding because
if you forget about the fact that well
only so truly understands begins
understanding of the suta then your
put's understanding of that suta will
become adequate and you think well I'm
not s about but I understood the suta
it's good enough if I understand many
other sutas on this good enough level it
will add up no it won't it doesn't it
can add up maybe in a sense that then it
will make you revisit all those sutas
and start seeing even more in them sure
but again the only time you will start
looking for more is if you don't think
you completely understood it if you take
your understanding that you will
inevitably have anything you read
anything and you make sense out of it
that's a degree of understanding but if
you any understanding you have you take
a pinch with a pinch of salt read other
Su then you come back to it and then see
if you can understand even more and more
and more and more and as I said if you
do that rightly uh that's the 50% of the
right instruction is being taken
rightly uh and then if you develop
yasara through not attending wrong
things that's why the constant talking
about inuring things rightly on the
right level sense restraint withdrawal
cacy because it was hard enough to
discern Yara back in the day it's even
harder today uh so if you pair those two things
today uh so if you pair those two things
and know what to keep looking for and
not fall into complacent view that
because you made sense out of dharm thus
you understand the dharm while at the
same time you know you're not a s that's
a contradiction in terms so if you don't
fall into that view then you would be
keep well you would keep pushing forward
you would keep trying to to understand
the worst is to think you understood
that which you didn't or you understood
that which there still carries um more
to be understood like Yono means wise
reflection fine I won't think about it
anymore it refers to Yono whenever
Buddha says yonara means wise reflection
I engage with wise reflection and
because of that you won't look for the
immediacy of that term that actually is
a factor for arising of the Right View
those who listen to the Buddha and got
The Right View upon him hearing his
sentence is because Yono has been there
waiting developed they didn't have to go
home and wisely reconsider what they
read or heard just upon hearing it
things slaughtered in place so that's
why it needs to be taken on that deeper
level of of a more immediate level and
you could pretty much take all the other
key terms and Notions from the sutas on
that uh on that deeper uh more immediate
uh level that doesn't invalidate your
current understanding of it but it
certainly upgrades it and um and then
again it would make even more sense how
oh if somebody truly understands the
entire instruction from the Buddha back
in the day from the beginning till the
end at the end of the talk they became
an arahant you realize well that's why
it wasn't like some magic like their
mind was already there thoroughly
established with Yono imperturbable Yono
through development of sense restraint
um not giving not attending not
emphasizing things that shouldn't be
emphasized and now the Buddha just just
just described that for them in terms
they should see it and they saw it
because it was already there unwavering
mind was already developed tained to an
unwavering extent to a sufficient extent
and then arship was the result of it
there like no nothing nothing magical I
mean you could say it's magical
experience but really they did the work
through that diligent and development of
those Enlightenment factors